<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, aldermen, and citizens of London at the Church of St. Mary le Bow, September the second, 1684, being the anniversary fast for the dreadful fire in the year 1666 by Benjamin Calamy ...</title>
            <author>Calamy, Benjamin, 1642-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31846</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5723</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13689501</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13689501</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101389</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31846)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101389)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 840:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, aldermen, and citizens of London at the Church of St. Mary le Bow, September the second, 1684, being the anniversary fast for the dreadful fire in the year 1666 by Benjamin Calamy ...</title>
                  <author>Calamy, Benjamin, 1642-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah LVII, 21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:101389:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Tulſe Mayor,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martis decimo ſexto die Septemb.</hi> 1684. <hi>Annoque Regni Regis</hi> Caroli <hi>Secundi</hi> Angliae, <hi>&amp;c. trigeſimo ſexto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THis Court doth deſire Dr. <hi>Calamy</hi> to Print his Sermon Preached at <hi>Bow</hi>-Church on the Second of <hi>September</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, (being the Day of Humiliation for the Great Fire in the Year 1666.) before the Lord Mayor, and Aldermen, and Citizens of this City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WAGSTAFFE.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101389:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Right Honourable The Lord Mayor, ALDERMEN, AND CITIZENS of <hi>LONDON,</hi> At the Church of St. <hi>Mary le Bow, September</hi> the Second, 1684.</p>
            <p>BEING THE Anniverſary Faſt FOR THE DREADFUL FIRE In the Year 1666.</p>
            <p>By <hi>BENJAMIN CALAMY</hi> D. D. Vicar of St. <hi>Laurence Jewry,</hi> and one of His MAJESTY's Chaplains in Ordinary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101389:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101389:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE Sir Henry Tulſe LORD MAYOR OF THE City of London, And to the Honourable COURT of ALDERMEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN Obedience to Your Lordſhips Commands I have publiſhed this following Sermon, and now humbly preſent it to Your favourable Acceptance. The Diſcourſe was ſuited to the Day, plain and ſerious; the Subject Matter of it or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and common, but highly uſeful and ſeaſonable.
<pb facs="tcp:101389:3"/>And if any of the Inhabitants of this great City are by the reading of it perſuaded to, or better eſtabliſhed in the ſtrict Practiſe of their Religion in all its ſeveral Duties, which reſpect either God or Man, I have obtained my whole Deſign both in the Preaching and Printing of it.</p>
            <p>I beg Your Lordſhips Pardon, if I take this Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to renew my moſt thankful Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thoſe many particular Favours I have received from Your Lordſhip, by which I am bound ever to remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed> Your moſt Obedient and Humble Servant, <hi>Benjamin Calamy.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101389:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before The Lord Mayor, On <hi>September</hi> the Second, 1684.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAIAH LVII. 21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>There is no peace, ſaith my God, to the wicked.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is not to be imagined, that the Deſign of this Anniverſary Faſt is barely to call to mind thoſe diſmal Days wherein this Famous City was laid in Aſhes, and to hear the doleful Relation of that amazing Providence; but it was intended as an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for the Exerciſe of ſerious Repentance: and to that purpoſe we are now met, to lament our Sins, and humble our Souls in God's preſence, and to renew our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101389:4"/>Reſolutions againſt all thoſe Courſes which once pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down ſuch remarkable Judgments upon this Place, and will, unleſs we reform them, at laſt prove our utter Ruine: And to improve the Conſideration of that dreadful Calamity to the ſame pious purpoſes, is my preſent Deſign, from the Words now read unto you.</p>
            <p>In the Verſes immediately foregoing my Text the Prophet endeavours to revive the drooping Spirits of thoſe amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> now in <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity, who were truly penitent for their paſt Sins, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called, <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>the humble and contrite ones,</hi> with the Promiſe of God's Mercy to them, in bringing them back at laſt to their Native Country; aſſuring thoſe <hi>who put their truſt in God,</hi> that, tho' now far baniſhed from it, yet they ſhould again <hi>poſſeſs their land, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the holy Mountain. For God will not contend for ever,</hi> v. 16. <hi>neither will he be always wroth.</hi> He knoweth our weakneſs, and how unable we are to ſtand before him, when he is angry. He obſerved therefore their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>v.</hi> 18. and how they amended their <hi>ways,</hi> and would <hi>heal them,</hi> and conduct them ſafely to their own Land, with abundance of Joy and Peace.</p>
            <p>But if, after ſo ſignal deliverance, they ſhould again fall back to their old Courſes; if, forgetful both of thoſe ſore Evils God had inflicted on them for their Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and of his wonderful Mercy ſhewn in redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them from their Captivity, they ſhould wantonly return, when reſtored, to their former Provocations, he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101389:4"/>tells them, that they ſhould by ſad Experience find, that the ſame Effects would ſtill follow the ſame Cauſes, that Sin and Irreligion would again deſtroy their Peace, and bring down God's ſeverer Vengeance againſt them: ſo that they ſhould be <hi>like the troubled ſea, which cannot reſt, v.</hi> 20. always unquiet and unſetled, in continual diſtraction and confuſion. And now, that they might not in the leaſt doubt of the truth of all this, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it by the Authority of God himſelf, <hi>There is no peace, ſaith my God, to the wicked.</hi> They muſt never look to be an happy, flouriſhing People, as long as their Lives and Manners were ſo corrupt and degenerate. This ſome Learned Men take to be the ſtrict meaning of the Words, and thus I ſhall now underſtand them.</p>
            <p>Under this Word <hi>Peace</hi> in <hi>Scripture</hi> is often compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended all manner of outward Happineſs and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and taking it in this large ſenſe, the Words do not then reſpect wicked men conſidered ſingly by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but as they are joyned together in Society and Community; to whom the Prophet declares, from the Mouth of God, That there is nothing ſo deſtructive of the Political Happineſs or Welfare of any People, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Vice and Wickedneſs. Religion doth not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſecure the inward Peace and Tranquillity of our Minds, and provide for our future Felicity in the other World, but doth mightily promote the temporal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of any Kingdom or City in this: And, on the contrary, Vice and Wickedneſs, eſpecially where it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101389:5"/>abounds, and is become faſhionable and creditable, and hath infected all Sorts and Ranks of Men, doth certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undermine, and will by degrees overthrow the Peace and Happineſs of any Society or Community. <hi>There is no peace, ſaith my God, to the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many and weighty are the Arguments by which men may be moved to Repentance and Amendment of Life. There is no Capacity we can be conſider'd in, no Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we can ſtand in, but Religion is of mighty uſe and advantage to us in it; and, on the contrary, Sin and Wickedneſs infinitely prejudicial and miſchievous. But I cannot think any Conſideration more proper to this Aſſembly, or to the Occaſion of this Solemnity, than what my Text ſuggeſts to us, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſerviceableneſs of True Religion to the Publick Good and Intereſt, and the malign Influence that Vice and Impiety hath upon any Kingdom, City, or Body Politick; whence we may learn, to what Cauſes ought to be imputed that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Judgment of Fire, which once laid this City waſte; as alſo, what is the moſt ſucceſsful Expedient to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this City, and the whole Kingdom, from any ſuch Publick Calamity for the time to come.</p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this Subject, I ſhall firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the Truth of what is here affirmed, and then make ſuch particular Application to our ſelves, as may be moſt ſuitable to the Occaſion of our meeting at this day.</p>
            <p>In order to the proving of this, That Wickedneſs
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101389:5"/>doth obſtruct the Peace and Happineſs of any People or Society, I ſhall inſiſt on theſe three Arguments.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The natural tendency of Vice and Wickedneſs.</item>
               <item>2. The Conſideration of God's Providence, and his righteous Government of the World.</item>
               <item>3. The Experience of all Ages.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. How contrary Vice and Wickedneſs is to the Temporal Peace and Proſperity of any Kingdom or City, will appear from the natural tendency of Sin and Irreligion, which neceſſarily produceth many Publick Miſchiefs, which we can no ways avoid, but by leaving thoſe Sins which are the natural Cauſes of them: and, on the other ſide, the true Fear of God, and hearty Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Laws, do in their own nature, and direct conſequence, conduce to the Publick Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Moſt of the Duties of Religion are ſo abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the good Order, Quiet, and Peace of Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that Men have found it highly expedient to oblige one another to the obſervance of them by Civil Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Humane Laws: and ſhould the wiſeſt Men, the greateſt Politicians on Earth, ſet themſelves to find out the beſt and moſt uſeful Rules of Living, for the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Publick Peace and Happineſs of Kingdoms or Cities, they could pitch on no other but thoſe very ſame Precepts which God hath given us, of doing to all as we would be done unto, of mutual Love and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of ſtrict Juſtice and Temperance, of Faithfulneſs, and Meekneſs, and Patience. And leſt Men ſhould not be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101389:6"/>ſufficiently moved by the Divine Threatnings, the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Governments have always added Temporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to reſtrain Men within thoſe Bounds which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion hath preſcribed to us, without which all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Societies would preſently fly in pieces, and the World be over-run with Diſorder and Confuſion.</p>
            <p>It is a common Obſervation, That even Societies of wicked, lawleſs Men, who combine together to do miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief and injury to others, yet are forced to bind them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the practiſe of ſome Vertues, without which they cannot hold together. Thieves and Robbers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to be juſt and faithful to each other; and the very Powers of Darkneſs take care to preſerve Order and Unity amongſt their miſerable Subjects, without which, our Saviour tells us, the Devil's Kingdom cannot ſtand.</p>
            <p>But what Effect Religion hath upon Societies, will better be underſtood, if we conſider diſtinctly, firſt, the Principles of Religion, and then the Duties and Offices of it, and ſhew what Influence they both have upon the Publick Peace and Safety.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As for the Principles of Religion, the Belief of a God, and a Future Life, theſe are the very Baſis and Foundation of all Society, without which it can never ſubſiſt. This is ſufficiently acknowledged even by <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts</hi> themſelves, whilſt they affirm, as <hi>Tully</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>the whole Opinion of the Gods to have been feigned by wiſe Men, for the ſake of the Commonwealth, that ſo Religion might engage thoſe to their Duty, whom Reaſon could not.</hi> They
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101389:6"/>would ſuſpect all Religion to have been a Politick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of Civil Sovereigns and crafty Law-makers, by the Fears of an Inviſible Power to keep Men in awe and order. <hi>There was a time at firſt,</hi> as they tell us, <hi>when Mens Lives were diſorderly and brutiſh, and the Will of the ſtronger was the onely Law: After which they conſented and agreed together to make Civil Laws, that ſo the Diſorderly might be puniſhed. But Temporal Penalties not being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to deter Men from ſecret Injuries, at laſt when Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind hapned to be under one <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarch, there aroſe a mighty ſagacious and prudent Prince or Miniſter of State, the Author of a further Invention, to ſcare Men from pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate as well as from open Injuries; and that was, by feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a God, Immortal and Omnipotent, who hears, and ſees, and takes notice of all things: and from hence the noiſe of a God came to ring over the whole World, and to fill all Places with Temples and Altars.</hi> Thus they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent Religion as a meer Engine of State, and Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Government, to poſſeſs the Minds of the Vulgar with the Belief of a God, and a Life to come, thereby to render them more tame and gentle, ſubmiſſive and obedient: And this alone hath continued the Cheat in the World to this day, becauſe this Device hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo ſtrangely ſucceſsful for the Ends of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to ſerve which it was firſt invented; and hence it became the Intereſt of States and Kingdoms to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and cheriſh ſuch Apprehenſions in thoſe ſubject to them.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101389:7"/>
            <p>I have not time now to confute or expoſe this wild Suppoſition, for which there is not the leaſt Ground or Evidence; but I think I may draw theſe three Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions from this Atheiſtical Suggeſtion, which will be not a little to my preſent purpoſe. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That by the Confeſſion of the greateſt Enemies and Haters of Religion, the Principles of it are very uſeful and beneficial to Mankind Admitting all they ſay for true, yet it is great pity that Religion hath not its Foundation in Nature and Reaſon, it being ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to Government, and it laying ſuch ſtrong Obligations upon People to quiet and orderly living, that without it the Earth would be but one vaſt howl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wilderneſs, and Men ſo many Beaſts of Prey, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually worrying and devouring one another.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Principles of Religion were all falſe, if they be all Impoſture and Cheat, yet it is beſt for Men to be kept ignorant of this Secret, the Belief of them being of ſo great conſequence to the Welfare of all Kingdoms and Societies. If we are impoſed upon in the Matters of Religion, yet it is againſt our Intereſt to be undeceived.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It follows further, That they are the greateſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Mankind, and of the Nation or City they live in, and ought to be looked upon, and avoided as the moſt dangerous Diſturbers of the Publick Peace, and the very Peſts of Humane Society, who go about to root this Belief out of the Minds of Men, and to ſet them free from thoſe Fears which Religion propounds
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101389:7"/>to them; this being the readieſt and ſhorteſt way to diſſolve all Government, and disband all Societies.</p>
            <p>Take away the ſenſe of Religion, and the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Superiour Inviſible Power, who takes notice of all we do, and will one day call us to a ſtrict account, and Men have no other Rule left to guide themſelves by, but their own Will and particular Intereſt. All Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are then broken down: Every Man may do any thing he can ſafely, and nothing is unlawful to be done by him who hath but Power enough to juſtifie it, and can defend himſelf when he hath done it: There can be no Security to Governours, no Confidence one in another; there is nothing we can call our own, no Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to ſtand to our Promiſes and Covenants, or to obey the Laws of the Society we are Members of, any further than we ſee it is for our own private Benefit; and of this then every Man is Judge for himſelf. So true is that excellent Saying of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> That <hi>a City might be as well built in the Air, without any Earth to ſtand upon, as a Commonwealth can be either conſtituted or preſerved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſupport of Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If we conſider the Offices and Duties of Religion, we ſhall find moſt of them plainly ſubſervient to the Publick Peace and Happineſs; and, on the contrary, Irreligious Practiſes do naturally lead to Diſorder and Confuſion, ſo that there is hardly any Vice, but what bringeth ſome notable Damage to the Publick. So ſaith St. <hi>James,</hi> c. 4.1. <hi>Whence come wars and fightings amongſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101389:8"/>you? are they not hence, even from your luſts, which war in your members?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unbounded Avarice and Ambition, implacable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Revenge, unmeaſurable coveting of what is other Mens, unjuſt Oppreſſion of thoſe whom we have at any advantage, theſe are the fruitful Parents of Publick Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances and Confuſions. Luxury, and Senſuality, and Prodigality conſume the Wealth and Treaſure of a Nation. Idleneſs, Intemperance, and untamed Luſt, effeminate and enfeeble the Minds of Men, deſtroys their Courage and Spirit, and ſo lays them open to the Aſſaults of their Enemies.</p>
            <p>Irreligion and Prophaneneſs break in pieces the Bands of Community; and they, who make nothing of thoſe Obligations which God's Laws have laid upon them, will not be held by any that Men can make; and their Allegiance to their Earthly Sovereign is always to be ſuſpected, who have caſt off all Subjection to the Lord of Heaven and Earth.</p>
            <p>Lying, Falſhood, Injuſtice, Uncharitableneſs, and contempt of an Oath, (which is the certain Effect of vain Swearing in common Diſcourſe) theſe deſtroy all mutual Good-will, and Faith, and Truſt amongſt Men, which are the great Joynts and Ligaments by which the Members of any Body Politick are knit and faſtned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>Unreaſonable Appetites and Paſſions make Men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie and troubleſom one to another, and are the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101389:8"/>Cauſes of Enmity, Diviſion, Strife, and every Evil work; and by diſuniting of Men one from another, they apparently make way for the diſſolution of any Society.</p>
            <p>Pride and Diſcontent naturally make Men Factious and Unpeaceable, diſpoſe Men to endeavour Changes and Alterations, in hopes of bettering themſelves; and the Sin of Schiſm, and unneceſſary breach of Chriſtian Communion, even as a Phyſical Cauſe, doth uſher in the Ruine of the State, as well as of the Church.</p>
            <p>Thus I might run over all manner of Sins, and ſhew how they all, more or leſs, weaken the Sinews and Strength of the beſt-conſtituted Government, where they are commonly practiſed. So that ſhould God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſtand Neuter, and not concern himſelf in the Affairs of this lower World; had he left Mankind, as the <hi>Epicureans</hi> thought, wholly to their own Counſel and Conduct, and ſhould never trouble himſelf to inflict any Evils upon us for our Diſobedience to him; yet the natural Conſequences of our own Sins, the ill Effects they have upon the Kingdom or City we live in, would be no little Puniſhment for them. And this we learn from the Mouth of God himſelf, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.29. <hi>O that there were ſuch an heart in them, that they would fear me, and keep all my commandments always, that it might be well with them, and with their children for ever!</hi> Where God is pleaſed to repreſent it, as a Learned Man obſerves on that Place, as <hi>a thing e'en quite out of his own power, to make it well with an impious people: O that they would
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101389:9"/>fear me, that ſo it might be well with them!</hi> as if it were impoſſible, from the very Nature of the thing, for God to make a People happy, whiſt they continued vicious and unreformed: <hi>So neceſſary, ſo indiſpenſible are Piety and Vertue to the Eſtabliſhment of a Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Religion inſpirits Men with all thoſe good Qualities and Diſpoſitions that tend to Peace and Unity, which is the Life and Soul of all Society: It extirpates all thoſe Vices and Paſſions which are the Cauſes of Enmity and Diviſion; teacheth every Man to keep his own Rank and Place, to mind his proper Duty, to give to every one his Due, and to prefer the Publick Good before his own Private Advantage. It inclineth and obligeth Men to all mutual Offices of Love and Kindneſs. It maketh Magiſtrates juſt and merciful, Subjects faithful and obedient, out of Conſcience, for God's ſake. It ſecureth every Mans Intereſt, and Fortune, and Reputation, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man in his particular Station contributing his beſt to the Common Welfare.</p>
            <p>We cannot poſſibly frame in our Minds the Idea of a more happy State of things, than would preſently be, if the Fear of God, and Love of Righteouſneſs, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Practice of Religion, did every where prevail amongſt us. There would be then no Diſcontents, nor Complaints heard in our Streets, no Jealouſies or fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Suſpicions, no Sidings, or Parties, or divided Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, no Separations and opprobrious Nick-names of Diſtinction, which are the mortal Diſeaſes of the Body
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101389:9"/>Politick, and the never-failing Symptoms of a decaying State. How ſafely and pleaſantly ſhould we all live! A Kingdom or City bleſs'd with ſuch Inhabitants, what would it be but an Heaven upon Earth? And tho it is hardly to be hoped that ever ſuch an happy Change ſhould be found amongſt us, that Religion ſhould gain ſuch an univerſal Conqueſt over the Minds of all Men, yet let me ſay, That to thoſe ſmall Reliques of Vertue and Piety which are yet to be found amongſt us, it is chiefly owing that Mankind live together in any tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Peace and Security.</p>
            <p>Thus Sin hath a natural tendency to make not onely the Sinner himſelf miſerable, but the Society alſo of which he is a Member; whilſt, as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.34. <hi>Righteouſneſs exalteth a nation,</hi> raiſeth it to the higheſt degree of Proſperity and Glory. To which I ſhall onely add the Obſervation of that great <hi>Roman</hi> General <hi>Scipio,</hi> That <hi>it was impoſſible for any State or City to be happy, ſtantibus moenibus, ruentibus moribus, tho' their Walls were never ſo firm and good, if their Manners were decayed and corrupted.</hi> But this is not all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt conſider, that God Almighty is no idle and indifferent Spectator of the Actions of Men. He is no ſuch ſoft and delicate Being, (as ſome have imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him) taking his own Eaſe and Repoſe within the ſpacious Circuits of Heaven, whilſt, unconcerned at the Affairs of Mortals, he lets this lower World go as it will. No, his careful Providence is extended even to the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101389:10"/>meaneſt thing which his Power created; much more it is converſant about whole Kingdoms, Cities, and great Societies of Men: And this is the ſetled Courſe and Method of his Government.</p>
            <p>Tho' he often ſuffers ſome particular Men to thrive and flouriſh in their Sin and Impiety, and doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways call ſingle Perſons to an Account in this Life, but reſerves them for the future Vengeance; yet he dealeth otherwiſe with Bodies Politick: He will not permit them ordinarily to paſs unpuniſhed in this State, this Life being the onely time wherein he can reckon with Men as joyn'd together in Civil Societies; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, beſides all the Evils Men bring upon themſelves by their Wickedneſs, the Great Sovereign of the World doth by way of Exemplary Juſtice inflict ſore and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolating Calamities, ſuch as Plague, Fire, Sword, Famine, and the like, as the due Reward of their incurable Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy in Sin and Diſobedience. Prevailing and crying Sins of a Nation or City, without timely Repentance, never ſcape Publick Judgments.</p>
            <p>And indeed, it is in a manner neceſſary for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the World, and preſerving ſome good Order in it, and keeping up in Men the awe of an Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Power, upon high and publick Provocations, when Men inſolently bid open Defiance to the Laws of God; I ſay, it is neceſſary that God ſhould manifeſt his Power and Diſpleaſure, by ſome remarkable Puniſhments, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on Places generally infamous for their foul In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101389:10"/>towards, and horrid Contempt of his Divine Majeſty.</p>
            <p>When Sin and Irreligion mightily abounds, and hath gained reputation amongſt fooliſh people, and, like a great Flood, carries all before it; when it hath once got an Head, and formed a ſtrong Party, and Men of all Conditions and Qualities are engaged on the ſide of Vice and Profaneneſs, all Reaſon and Argument ſhall at ſuch a time be eaſily run down, and the <hi>ſoft voice</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not then be heard: God muſt appear in a <hi>great Storm, with Thunder and Lightning,</hi> as he did of old to the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> if he would have the Inhabitants of the Earth look up to him, or would convince them of their Folly and Danger.</p>
            <p>Such publick Judgments are rightly compared to publick Executions, which are ſometimes neceſſary for the Support of the Government, and making People to ſtand in dread of the Laws. They ſerve eſpecially to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite in the generality of Mankind a more quick and lively ſenſe of God's Power over, and Preſence with them, to rouſe Men out of that Stupidity and dull Lethargy, which long and proſperous continuance in Sin betrays them into. <hi>I will cauſe you to paſs under the rod,</hi> ſaith God by the Prophet, <hi>and then ſhall you,</hi> and all that hear and ſee it, <hi>know, that I am the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, did not that miſerable Fate, which befel <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorra,</hi> ſerve to awaken the neighbouring Cities &amp; Countries, when they beheld the bright Flames to aſcend
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101389:11"/>towards Heaven, to inquire into the Cauſes of ſuch Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity, and to examine themſelves, whether they were guilty of the ſame Sins, which had ſo highly incenſed God? And would not they have been glad to have been at good terms and at peace with that Almighty Being, who hath ſuch dreadful Puniſhments in ſtore for the Refractory and Impenitent?</p>
            <p>And was it not thus with us, at the the time of the late terrible Conflagration, which we are this day more particularly to call to our minds? I appeal to all amongſt you, that were then preſent at it: Did you not then humbly acknowledge the Hand of God in it? Did you not then accuſe your ſelves and did not your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences loudly charge you with thoſe Sins, that you could not but think did fully deſerve ſo ſevere Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? Did not ſome of you blame your Covetouſneſs, and niggardly hoarding up thoſe many Goods, which now ſuddenly periſhed in the mercileſs Flames? Did not others of you curſe your Injuſtice, and Falſeneſs in your Trades? others, your Intemperance and Riot? and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in this City, their odious Hypocriſie, and baſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting Religion to unworthy Ends, which, with other Sins, provoked God to ſo great Anger? Did you not then make many ſerious Promiſes of better living, ſhould you any ways eſcape, or ever recover ſo great a Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity? What would you not then have undertook, nay, performed, onely to have been aſſured, that in ſo ſhort a time you ſhould be again reſtored to your Dwellings,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101389:11"/>Trades, and Poſſeſſions; that this City ſhould ſo ſoon riſe out of its Rubbiſh and Aſhes, and all of us return to live in greater ſplendour and eaſe than we did before? And O had we lived anſwerably to thoſe Vows and Promiſes which this ſurpriſing Providence did then extort from us in the day of our Fears, what an holy, what an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py City had this been!</p>
            <p>But, alas! do not the ſame Vices, to ſay no worſe, reign amongſt us, which did before Sixty ſix? So that we have great cauſe to fear, tho' I am loth to ſpeak it, that it is e'en now time for God to think of ſome more ſmarting Puniſhment, more grievous than any we have yet felt, which may give ſome check to the overflowing Atheiſm and Wickedneſs of this Age. And doubt not, but he will do it in his due time, unleſs we ſtop his Hand by a general Reformation.</p>
            <p>God doth not take any delight in ſuch Severities. It is no pleaſure to him to make ſuch havock in the World. This is his <hi>ſtrange work:</hi> He is very loth to be brought to it. He doth not <hi>willingly grieve</hi> any particular Man; much leſs doth he love to exerciſe his Power in laying whole Cities and Kingdoms waſte: But onely, when he is concerned in Honour to vindicate his Authority, his Laws, his Name, from bold Profanations, and open bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd Affronts, then neither our Wealth, nor Power, nor Policy, can ſecure us from the Omnipotent Arm of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice. And indeed, it is very great Impudence for us to expect or hope, that God ſhould bleſs or protect
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101389:12"/>that People who live in open Rebellion againſt him.</p>
            <p>By all this it appears, that Vice and Wickedneſs is not onely by its own Malignity apt to deſtroy us; but alſo, where it prevails and abounds, doth, as it were, neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate God Almighty to viſit ſuch a People, eſpecially when they are irreclaimable by any gentler Methods, with ſuch ſignal and remarkable Judgments, as may keep the World in ſome awe of him, and make them confeſs, That <hi>there is a God who judgeth the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas the general Practice of Religion recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends and intitles us to the Almighty's Protection, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages him on our ſide, ſecures to us the conſtant Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours and Aids of Divine Providence. God will watch over our Cities and Houſes, will bleſs our Land with Increaſe, will deliver us from all our Enemies, and think nothing too much, or too good for us. <hi>Seek ye the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and the righteouſneſs thereof, in the firſt place, and all theſe things ſhall be added to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In the laſt place, I appeal to the Experience of all Ages,; and we ſhall certainly find the State and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any Kingdom or Society to have been more or leſs proſperous, according to the Manners that have prevailed amongſt them: Which was of old acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the <hi>Orator,</hi> in that known Saying, <hi>Omnia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpera eveniunt colentibus Deos, adverſa ſpernentibus; The People that have a care of Religion, are always ſucceſsful; but unhappy, when they are Irreligious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God indeed may defer pouring forth his Wrath for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101389:12"/>a while, to give Men time and ſpace of Repentance; but at laſt, when <hi>their iniquities are full,</hi> (as the Scripture expreſſeth it) Divine Vengeance hath overtaken them, which hath commonly been ſo much the ſorer, the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger it hath been delaied. If we look therefore upon any one whole Kingdom, or great City, as joyned together in one Society, we ſhall generally find, that according as Vertue, Juſtice, Temperance, Sincerity, and Fidelity hath flouriſhed amongſt them, ſo long have they thrived, grown Great, Powerful, and Wealthy, and abounded with all Good things; and never hardly were there any Times or Places famous for Publick Prophaneneſs, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries, and Contempt of Things Sacred, but they alſo remarkably bore the ſad Tokens of the Divine Diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>There is nothing more evident than this in the whole Story of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that as long as they continued conſtant to the Worſhip of the True God, in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he had preſcrib'd to them, they either lived in Peace, or their Arms were always ſucceſsful, and their Land flowed with Milk and Honey: But when at any time they fell into Idolatry, it was always attended with ſome mortal Diſeaſe, or the devouring Sword, or a long Captivity. Their Sins would poyſon their Air, blaſt their Corn, weaken their Hands in the Day of Battel, till at length, after many various Diſpenſations of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Judgment, when they refuſed to be amended by the Preaching of the Son of God himſelf, their City was
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101389:13"/>ſacked and burnt by the <hi>Roman</hi> Legions, their glorious Temple demoliſhed, their Polity diſſolved, and their whole Nation involved in one common Ruine.</p>
            <p>But becauſe it is uſually objected in this Caſe, That God hath not dealt ſo with other People and Nations, as he did with the <hi>Jews,</hi> whoſe Political Sovereign and Governour he was after a more peculiar manner; and that we are not to argue from Gods ſpecial Providences towards them, nor draw his Proceedings with <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> into a Preſident to other Kingdoms and Cities; we may therefore ſearch into Profane Hiſtories, and every Age will give in ſome Teſtimony to this Truth.</p>
            <p>If we inquire into the Cauſes of the Diſſolution of thoſe Potent Empires and States which once were ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in the World, or of the Deſtruction of thoſe great and populous Cities, of which the bare Names onely now remain, and we can hardly find out the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they once ſtood, we ſhall ſee abundant rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to impute their Ruine to their own Follies and Wickedneſs. Either they fell into Parties and Diviſions, and ſo crumbled into Pieces, or their Strength and Wealth being waſted by Eaſe and Luxury, they were expoſed to the Fury of a Foreign Enemy; or elſe by the Cry of their enormous Sins provoked God to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw them by Inundations, Earthquakes, Fire, or ſome ſuch depopulating Judgments. This is particularly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by almoſt all that treat of this Argument, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe mighty Revolutions which hapned in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101389:13"/>the Four firſt <hi>Monarchies,</hi> as they are commonly called</p>
            <p>That which gave occaſion to the enlarging the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonian</hi> Monarchy, and made it ſpread ſo faſt and wide, was neither their own Courage nor Counſel, but the Tranſgreſſions &amp; Provocations of the Eaſtern Nations, which moved God to give them over as a Prey to the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> whom he calls by the Prophet <hi>the rod of his anger,</hi> and made uſe of <hi>to deſtroy and cut off nations not a few.</hi> And when the Lord by him had performed his whole Work, and the Sins of <hi>Babylon</hi> were ripe for Vengeance, then did God raiſe up <hi>Cyrus.</hi> who at a time of a great Feaſt, in the midſt of their Jollity and Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, entred into that City, and fulfilled all thoſe Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings which God's Prophets had often denounced againſt that People.</p>
            <p>When, in proceſs of time, the <hi>Perſians</hi> had ſunk into the ſame Vices for which God had deſtroyed the <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,</hi> how eaſily and ſuddenly were they conquered and over-run by <hi>Alexander</hi> and his <hi>Grecians,</hi> to whom God gave Succeſs vaſtly beyond their own Hopes, greater than they themſelves could expect, either from the Number or Strength of their Armies?</p>
            <p>After which, the <hi>Grecians</hi> themſelves, being ſoftned by <hi>Perſian</hi> Luxury, and infected with the Vices of <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſoon ſubmitted to the <hi>Romans;</hi> of whom the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Cicero</hi> affirms, <hi>Non calliditate ac robore, ſed Pietate &amp; Religione omnes gentes nationeſque ſuperaviſſe; That they overcame all the Nations, not by Force or Craft, but by piety and Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:101389:14"/>
            <p>And of them it is commonly taken notice of in the <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtory, That whilſt their Senators and People inviolably maintained that ſtrict Juſtice, Faithfulneſs, and Sobriety, that was ſo remarkable in the firſt Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of that great Empire, ſo long they flouriſhed, and enlarged their Dominions, till at laſt they were them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves enſlaved to the Vices of all the Nations they had ſubdued; and then how miſerably were they haraſs'd with Civil Wars? and in the iſſue became a Prey to Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous People, God giving them up to be over-run by the <hi>Goths,</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> and <hi>Hunns,</hi> a cowardly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible People, if compared with the <hi>Romans,</hi> whoſe Succeſs yet was ſo ſtrange and unaccountable, that it could not be attributed to any Second Cauſes, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Hand of God, by them puniſhing the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> of the Weſt, then grown luxurious, and almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible by too much Felicity; as one of their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, <hi>Attila,</hi> ſtiled himſelf <hi>Flagellum Dei,</hi> God's Scourge to chaſtiſe the Wickedneſs of that People.</p>
            <p>Should we go no further than our own Country, our own Hiſtorians do all along obſerve, That thoſe great Deſolations which have been made in this Iſland, either by Foreign Invaſions, or Inteſtine Diviſions, or Infectious Diſeaſes, were always preceded by a notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous degeneracy and corruption of Manners. And againſt this, I believe, there are but few Exceptions; and where there are any, ſuch ſingle Inſtances are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God's ordinary eſtabliſh'd Rule and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101389:14"/>according to which we ought to expect he will always deal with us.</p>
            <p>By this time, I hope, you are all convinced of the evil nature of Vice and Wickedneſs, where it prevails and abounds; how contrary it is to, and deſtructive of the Publick Peace and Proſperity of any Kingdom or City. What remains, is to make ſome particular Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to our ſelves; which I ſhall do, by drawing theſe four Inferences.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hence we may learn, what great diſſervice they do unto, and what great diſhonour they bring upon Religion, who make pretence of it to the embroiling and diſturbance of Societies, and the breach of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace. Government and Society was ſetled in the World from the very beginning of it, by the general Providence of God, as being abſolutely neceſſary for our common Peace and Safety; and therefore nothing ought to be admitted, as any part of Revealed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is plainly inconſiſtent with this Prime and Original Inſtitution of God.</p>
            <p>I ſhould call that any thing rather than Religion, which makes Men Factious and Seditious, that prompts them to publick Outrages and Miſchiefs, that teaches them to burn Cities, and to make <hi>Stirs</hi> in a Kingdom, that inſpirits Men with a fierce Zeal which tranſgreſſes all Bounds, keeps no Place or Rank, obſerves no Mean or Decorum, that is promoted by ſecret Plots, and open Rebellion. If ſuch a Religion could be ſuppoſed to come
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101389:15"/>from Heaven, we might change the Words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and more truly ſay, That <hi>God was the Author not of Peace, but of Confuſion.</hi> But in this laſt Age the falſe Viſard and Mask of Religion hath been ſo often pulled off, and ſuch deformed Viſages have appeared to have been diſguiſed under it, that it is to be hoped, that the People of this Kingdom or City will not be eaſily cheated again into a Belief of the Honeſty or Good-meaning of any Perſons who joyn in a Party againſt the Lawful Government they live under, let their Pretences be what they will.</p>
            <p>It is otherwiſe with True Religion: It is quite of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Genius: It begets other Tempers and Spirits in Men. <hi>The wiſdom that comes from above, is firſt pure, then peaceable.</hi> Eſpecially our <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is ſo admirably fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the benefit and advantage of Societies, that were there no Obligation to the Practice of it from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations of another Life, yet all wiſe Men would think themſelves bound to the obſervance of the Chief Laws of our Saviour, were it onely out of reſpect to our Peace and Security in this preſent World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Since the Publick Welfare depends upon the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Men, we may thence conclude, how much it is the Intereſt, as well as Duty, of all Governours and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, in their ſeveral Places, to diſcourage and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh all Vice and Wickedneſs, and to countenance and promote True Religion, which is the great Inſtrument of Political Happineſs. The more the Fear of God, and the Practice of Righteouſneſs, prevails amongſt the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101389:15"/>the more eaſie and ſafe will the Government be; and therefore Religion doth fully reward the Civil Powers for all the Protection they can give it. True Religion tends ſo much to the Eſtabliſhment and Proſperity of any Nation, that they whoſe Office it is to look after the Publick Good, cannot do any thing better for themſelves, or for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple committed to their Charge; for the ſecuring their own juſt Authority, or maintaining the People in Peace and good Order, than by all means to preſerve and increaſe amongſt them a Reverence and Obedience to Almighty God and his Laws.</p>
            <p>This will keep them in firm ſubjection to their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours; this will unite them one to another in Love and Charity; and, which is never to be forgotten, this will procure Gods Bleſſing both upon Governours and People.</p>
            <p>And ſince Chriſtians are unhappily divided into ſeveral Denominations and Communions, take <hi>that Church,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, into your eſpecial Care and Patronage, whoſe Principles do moſt effectually contribute towards Mens orderly and quiet living together in Societies. If you can find any Church or Body of Chriſtians in the World, whoſe Doctrines are more Loyal, whoſe Government is better conſiſtent with Monarchy, whoſe Practices have been more peaceable at all times, than the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> I would e'en exhort you then to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake and renounce ours, and not onely tolerate, but eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh and ſet up that Church amongſt us. But in this cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly our Church hath no Competitor. Peaceable and quiet living under the Civil Government, always was, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101389:16"/>is ſtill the Glory of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> This Praiſe ſhe ſtands upon, and challengeth as due to her; and on this account doth ſhe with confidence recommend her ſelf, and all her true Members, to the Care and Protection of thoſe who are in Power and Authority, that they would be ſo juſt as to defend that Religion, that Church, which doth beſt defend and ſupport the Publick State.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence we may learn the true Cauſe of all thoſe Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Evils and Calamities that have befallen this Kingdom or City of late Years. Our Sins have been the Natural Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of ſome of them, the Meritorious Cauſes of others. Some we have brought upon our ſelves, as the neceſſary Effects of our own wicked Courſes; others God in Juſtice hath inflicted upon us, as the Puniſhment of our Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not now undertake to give in a Catalogue of thoſe many Sins that we in this City have been notoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guilty of. I had much rather leave that Work to your ſelves, for every Man to ſmite upon his own Breaſt, in which he will find a faithful Monitor, I mean his Conſcience, which will impartially tell him wherein he hath provoked God, and contributed to thoſe Judgments and Diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we have laboured under, if ſo be he will but patiently attend to its Suggeſtions, and give it leave and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity freely to ſpeak unto him. I am ſure it much more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes us all this Day to give Glory to God, and to take Shame to our ſelves, and to charge and accuſe our ſelves, than wholly to ſhift off all the Guilt &amp; Blame upon others.</p>
            <p>We are very apt indeed to impute theſe Publick Evils to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101389:16"/>other Cauſes; we are very curious in gueſſing at the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Inſtruments of them; and, which is worſt of all, too many amongſt us have been on all occaſions ready to lay all Publick Miſcarriages and Misfortunes at the Door of their Governours and Superiours: whereas the true Cauſe hath been from our ſelves; wherein no one can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit himſelf, tho' ſome far more innocent than others. But I ſhall rather chuſe to ſpend that little time your Patience can yet allow me, in perſuading you all to amend, than in ripping up the Vices of this Age, or City, or ſeveral Parties of Men amongſt us, for which we may juſtly ſuppoſe God hath viſited us with the Plague, this dreadful Fire, and (which was no leſs puniſhment) thoſe unnatural Diviſions and Heats which of late ſo violently broke out amongſt us, and threatned ſudden Ruine both to Church and State.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly, This Doctrine, which I have now proved to you, teacheth us the beſt Expedient to prevent ſuch Judgments for the future, and to ſettle us in firm Peace; which is, a general Reformation of our Lives and Manners.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God, the Caſe is much mended with us ſince the dreadful Burning of <hi>London.</hi> Our City hath been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years re-built, and that more ſplendid and glorious than before. We miſs not that number of Inhabitants who were ſwept away by the devouring Plague; nor hardly now do we feel any of the diſmal Effects of that terrible Fire. We ſeem to have weather'd out thoſe ſore Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And tho' of late our inteſtine Animoſities aroſe to ſuch an height, as that we all feared a woful Interruption of our Peace, yet God hath not as hitherto delivered us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101389:17"/>our own Hands, nor ſuffered us to deſtroy our ſelves. Nay, things tend at preſent towards an happy Settlement and Compoſure, and we begin to entertain hopes of living in quiet and ſafety, <hi>every man ſitting under his own vine and figtree.</hi> The Face of our Heavens is more clear and ſerene, and the black Clouds that preſag'd ſo dreadful a Storm, ſeem in ſome meaſure to be diſperſed. Yet let us not deceive our ſelves, and raſhly conclude, that <hi>the bitterneſs of death is now paſt:</hi> For, as I ſaid at firſt, the ſame Cauſes will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways produce the ſame Effects; and if the ſame Sins ſtill continue amongſt us, they will ſoon be attended with the ſame, or worſe Deſolations and Confuſions.</p>
            <p>If this be the natural Effect of prevailing Atheiſm, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, and Contempt of Religion, of Hatred and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, to weaken a Nation or People, to unſettle a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to unhinge the Government, and diſſolve all Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, let us not fondly think, that God Almighty will always miraculouſly interpoſe, and hinder theſe natural Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of Things. I ſay, God will not by extraordinary ways preſerve thoſe who obſtinately perſiſt in ſuch Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which naturally lead to their own Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>What Peace then can we expect amongſt us, if, after all theſe Viciſſitudes of Divine Providence towards us, we ſtill continue unreclaimed? When ſo many not onely neglect Religion, as a thing full of trouble, but ſcorn it, as unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of, and below them; when they are aſhamed to own their Belief or Fear of God, as if it were a ſign of a vulgar Spirit and mean Parts; when Men exerciſe their little Wits in abuſing and deriding the moſt ſerious and ſacred
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101389:17"/>things; What Villanies or Treaſons are not ſuch Men ripe for? What can oblige them, or tie their Hands?</p>
            <p>What Peace can there be in a Land or City where ſuch prodigious Debauchery reigns? where ſuch horrid Oaths and Perjuries abound? where Men ſin without ſhame, nay, glory in it as an Accompliſhment? <hi>Shall not God viſit for theſe things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, What Peace can there be, as long as there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main amongſt us ſuch bitter Envyings and Heart-burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſuch unchriſtian Separations and Contentions, ſuch Complaints and Diſcontents under ſuch happy Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Affairs, as that no Nation under Heaven is in the like? Theſe Vices and bad Diſpoſitions do naturally tend to our Ruine, beſides that they highly provoke God Almighty againſt us.</p>
            <p>I come not hither at this time to prophecy evil things againſt this City or Kingdom, nor would I amuſe you with needleſs Fears. I know well this hath been the great Art uſed by the Enemies of our Peace to raiſe Diſturban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces amongſt us, by poſſeſſing the Peoples Minds with ſtrange Jealouſies and Suſpicions, as if all things were run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ruine, and our Laws, Liberties, and Religion were all now at ſtake, and in extreme hazard. The onely thing I would earneſtly deſire you to conſider, is, That the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Danger we are in is from our ſelves, and conſequently, the way to preſerve our Peace is to reform our ſelves.</p>
            <p>And now at this time, when our moſt Gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, whom God long preſerve, hath taken particular care of us in this City, and hath done what in Him lieth to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101389:18"/>our undoing our ſelves, by putting the Government of it into ſafe Hands, and making ſeveral Publick Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations amongſt us, let us all in our ſeveral Stations be prevailed upon to do our part, every Man to turn from the evil of his ways, to fear God, to honour the King, to love his Neighbour, and mind his own private Duty, and to carry himſelf as becomes a Chriſtian, in all his ſeveral Relations he ſtands in to other Men, whereby we ſhall make God our Friend, and become hearty Friends one to another.</p>
            <p>Wiſe Men, by ſubtle Policies and Contrivances, may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert our Trouble and Danger for a while; but it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be well long with us, till the true Chriſtian Spirit of Love, and Charity, and Meekneſs, and Submiſſion, and Obedience, generally prevail amongſt us. Then indeed we ſhould ſoon ſee happy Days, and be freed from thoſe Fears and Diſturbances that have ſo long troubled our <hi>Iſrael.</hi> This is the beſt Project for Inſuring our new Houſes, and continuing thoſe great and manifold Mercies, both Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Temporal, which we in this City yet enjoy above any other People, to us, and to our Poſterity after us. How quiet, how ſetled a People ſhould we be, if we would but give credit to the Word of God, and follow our Bleſſed Saviour's Directions!</p>
            <p>And let not any one now think this a mean and pitiful Contrivance, and that himſelf hath far better Models and Projects for our Settlement, with which his politick Head labours and is in pain, till he be delivered of them in all Companies; ſince the State and Condition of Humane
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101389:18"/>Affairs is ſo diſpoſed by God's wiſe Providence, that there can be no laſting Peace without the practiſe of Vertue and Religion.</p>
            <p>Nor let any one think, that by thus reforming himſelf, he being but one, and perhaps but of ſmall Intereſt or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence in the City or Kingdom, it will be of very little concernment or advantage to the whole; for it is plain, that our Reformation muſt begin from ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſo proceed by degrees. It hath ſometimes indeed hapned, that there hath been a ſudden general Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Manners of Men throughout an whole City or Nation, as at <hi>Niniveh</hi> upon the Preaching of <hi>Jonah,</hi> upon ſome great Fright or extraordinary Judgment, when all the People, as one Man, have turned from the evil of their ways. But this is not our Caſe. Our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation muſt be accompliſhed (to borrow an Illuſtration) as this famous City of <hi>London</hi> was re-built; the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which was not all laid at the ſame time, nor <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Streets raiſed at once, but at firſt here a Houſe, and there a Houſe, to which others by degrees were joyn'd;</hi> and every private Man took care to build his own Houſe, and Authority took care of Publick Buildings, <hi>till at laſt ſingle Houſes were united into whole Streets, whole Streets into this beautiful and glorious City.</hi> Thus our Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt take its beginning from ſome few, from whom others may take Pattern and Encouragement, till at length it generally prevails; and why ſhould not good Examples be as effectual to reclaim this Age, as bad ones have been to debauch it?</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:101389:19"/>
            <p>To conclude all; Of all the great Arguments which our Religion affords us, to engage us to the leaving our Sins, and amending our Lives, I have this day inſiſted on this one, <hi>viz. That it is the onely certain Way and Method of ſecuring the Peace and Happineſs of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and of our Native Country.</hi> There may be many amongſt us whoſe Minds are not conſiderably affected with the Apprehenſions of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Rewards and Puniſhments; yet ſenſe of preſent Good or Evil ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth deep and laſting Impreſſions upon them: Who, tho they ſeem to have no regard for their everlaſting Happineſs in the other World, yet are ready to hazard their Lives, to expoſe their Eſtates and Fortunes, to ſacrifice all that Men uſually count dear, to the Service and Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their Country; and now one would think it ſhould not be altogether impoſſible to perſuade ſuch Perſons, for the ſame Reaſon, to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godlily in this preſent World. Shall a Man be ready at any time to venture and looſe his Life, and be loth to leave his Sins for the Publick Good and Safety?</p>
            <p>For your Countries ſake therefore, as you value the Welfare and Proſperity of this Kingdom, and this great City; as you deſire the continuance of thoſe many ſingular Bleſſings which yet thro' God's Patience we are poſſeſſed of; as you would avoid the repetition of thoſe Judgments you have already ſmarted under, or the inflicting of new and greater; in the Name of God, I exhort you all to repent and amend. Our Sins are many and great; they have (as I have ſhewn you) a natural tendency to Ruine and Confuſion; their Cry is gone up to Heaven againſt us. Delay not therefore to ſeek the Lord whilſt he is to be found, and to turn to him with your whole Hearts; and then ſhall God be reconciled to us, and turn away his Wrath from us, and prevent thoſe Judgments we fear, and remove thoſe we labour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and bleſs us with Peace, and Plenty, and Proſperity. <hi>Happy are the people that are in ſuch a caſe, yea, happy are the people whoſe God is the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I onely add, That ſuch a general Reformation of our own Tempers and Lives is vaſtly more our Duty, infinitely more for our private Advantage, and the Publick Good of the whole Kingdom, than all our Heat and Zeal for Reforming of Publick Grievances, or for amending the State, or other Men. <hi>There is no peace, ſaith my God, to the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
